Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim,
and you're probably wondering
what is this sewer tops,
the tops to the sewer?
And I don't know, maybe I
told you this story before
but once you get older,
you like to tell stories more.
And also you forget which
story you told people
and you didn't tell people.
So I apologize if I told
you this story before.
But I used to go to Mongolia a lot
to work in the different libraries there,
which have hundreds of thousands
of great Buddhist books.
One of the greatest,
some of the greatest Buddhist
libraries in the world.
So I remember one night
we were coming home from the library,
we were walking to the
hotel and it was dark.
They didn't have a lot of street lights
and I could see in front
of us on the street,
there was something moving,
and I look closer and
there's this sewer lid,
and it was opening.
There was a small animal
coming out of the sewer
in the dark, dark night.
Then the animal came out
and the sewer lid fell down,
and then this animal rushed past me
and almost touched me.
Then I was like, oh.
I asked my friend, my Mongolian friend,
I said, "What kind of animal is that?
Is it a wolf, it's living
in the sewer or something?
And they can open the sewer?"
He said, "No, no, no, that's not a wolf.
That's a kid. That's a human kid."
And I'm like, what?
He said, "Yeah, that's a
kid, that's a wild kid.
We call them wild kids."
I said, "What's a wild kid?"
He said, "Well, if your
parents die in Mongolia,
and if you don't have any other family,
you don't have money,
then you will live in the sewer.
You can live in the sewer."
I said, "Why they live in the
sewer, in the stinky sewer?"
They say, "It's cold here,
Geshe-la, the sewer is warm.
The sewer has shelter.
The snow, you're not
going to sit in the snow,
and the poo-poo makes the sewer warm,
and it's a warm place to stay.
So the kids will stay there."
I said, "What?
But that didn't look like a kid.
That looked like a wolf or something."
He said, "Yeah, they are
wild, they are really wild."
And he said, "Don't get close
to them, they will bite you."
I'm like, "What?"
He said, "Yeah, those are wild kids.
They cannot talk. They cannot speak.
They didn't have parents.
And no one taught them
to live like a human,
so they are living like a wolf.
They are living like an animal,
and if you get close to
them, they'll bite you.
They are like wild animals
and they don't talk.
They steal things from people.
In fact one of our staff
members had their bag stolen
by one of these wild kids."
And I was like, "Wow, that's so strange.:
Then I started to think.
I would be like that if
my mom didn't train me.
If my mom didn't teach me how to talk,
how to eat, how to put on clothes,
then I would be one of these
naked children running around
and biting tourists in Mongolia.
I would be the same, I'm not special,
I'm not different from them.
That's what Pabongka
Rinpoche is going say next.
So, DER MA ZAD
means not only did she take care of us
and watched over us,
that we talked about in the last session.
Hundreds of times a
day, she saved my life.
RKANG PA 'DZUG PA TSUN CHAD
She taught us to take our first steps.
I remember, so funny,
I remember Halloween night, and my mom,
my dad is teaching me how to chew gum
and how to blow bubbles,
and they were so excited.
My mom and dad,
"Look he's blowing a bubble,"
and I was like (blows air).
They teach you everything.
They teach you how to
take your first steps.
GTAM SMRA BA means they teach you
how to say your first words.
I remember my parents being really happy
when I learned a new word or something.
ZAS ZA STANGS how to eat
with a fork and a spoon or chopsticks
and don't eat with your fingers.
Your parents taught you that.
Even those, forget university,
forget reading Cervantes or Shakespeare,
just to eat without your fingers,
they taught you everything.
TSUN means everything
from that up. TSUN NAS
RIM BZHIN here's the RIM in Lam Rim,
which means one by one,
they taught you how to step,
how to talk. BSLAB PAS they taught you.
DA LTA 'GRO 'DUG DANG,
GTAM SMRA BA SOGS LA
THOGS PA MED PA 'DI BYUNG
That's why nowadays you and
I can stand up and walk,
or sit down politely,
or GTAM SMRA BA
we can have a conversation with somebody.
THOGS PA MED -- Asanga
What's it got to do
with talking or eating?
It's fluent.
It's, we don't have to think about it.
You just start talking THOGS PA MED Asanga
this THOGS PA MED means,
how do you say that?
Without any hesitation.
You can just start a conversation.
That's all due to them
teaching your first words.
The fact that you can THOGS PA MED
walk downstairs and get in your car,
is because they taught you
how to take your first step.
So don't forget.
MTHAR RANG GI DNGUL KHA GANG TZAM LA'ANG
Now they're going to talk
about a special subject,
which is the financial burden
that you were for your parents.
And it's bad, it's a lot.
I was coming here to the college,
I saw a lady driving
out of the parking lot
and she had two or three kids in the back.
The car was messed up. The
car was old and broken,
and I feel a little bit, offended.
I'm like why you drive the stupid car?
Then I look at the kids and I realize,
oh that's why you drive this stupid car,
because you have kids and
you can't afford them.
You're not like me. I can spend on,
I can buy a nice car, but she can't. Why?
I think the average cost of
a kid in the United States
is $30,000 a year.
You get three kids in the car.
I don't care what kind of job you have.
You can't have a new car.
You can have a junkie old car.
Because that's $90,000 a
year sitting in the back,
and that's unbelievable.
Of course, young people
don't think about that
before they have a baby.
But it's expensive, it's
extremely expensive.
You can't say, don't eat
this week. Or you can't say,
we're going to send you
to school without shoes.
You don't have a choice, you
have to spend that money.
So DNGUL KHA GANG TZAM LA'ANG
to make a single dollar.
DNGUL KHA means a single silver piece,
piece of silver.
She did whatever she had to do.
I remember, you got
that next picture Seiji,
where's that?
Yeah, it's the garbage truck.
I remember my mom, she was,
I remember what she did to make money.
So in my mom's time, in America,
my dad was not there.
They split up,
and my mom, suddenly
she has to make money,
and she never made money before.
She didn't know how to make money.
Because this is 1950's, 60's housewife.
She's not supposed to work.
Then suddenly, she has to make money,
and she's like, oh my god.
There's two jobs for women at that time.
It's a secretary or a school teacher.
So she decided to be a school teacher.
The pay is less than a garbage man.
I remember one day we're complaining,
me and the four brothers,
we are complaining.
Mom, why can't we have the more
expensive breakfast cereal?
She's like, "We can't afford it."
And we're like, "Mom, why not?
Our friends have a expensive
breakfast cereals."
She's like, and then the
garbage truck came by
and she said, "Look at that
guy, in the garbage truck."
And we're like, "Yeah."
She says, "He makes more
than a school teacher
in America, you understand?"
She said, "I'm doing my best.
This is the only job I can get.
And I can't, I'm struggling
for every single dollar."
And that's the way it was.
DNGUL KHA GANG TZAM LA'ANG SDIG DANG
Moms will do anything they have to do
to make that money, including prostitution
or whatever they have to do.
Doing any bad thing, they will do it.
For their kids they will do it.
There's many stories in the sutras,
of mothers who turned to prostitution
to support their kids or stuff like that.
A woman will do any kind of
degrading and disgusting job,
if it means that she can
give money to her children.
And your mom did the same thing,
and my mom did the same thing.
SDIG PA DANG, GTAM NGAN
She doesn't care what
people say about her.
She won't listen to
other people's opinion.
If she can make a dollar for you,
she will make a dollar for you.
SDUG BSNGAL KHYAD DU BSAD
She doesn't care how hard she has to work.
My mom worked, oh my gosh,
she came home from teaching all day
and then she had about three
hours of work after that,
to check the papers.
She didn't go to bed until
midnight or something
and then she got up in the
morning and did it again.
They don't care, because
they care about you.
They don't care about themselves.
I think my mom killed herself working.
She did it for you.
She doesn't care.
She worked herself to death just for you.
KHYAD DU BSAD NAS BSAGS PA'I
NOR RANG GI SHA LAS GCES PAR BZUNG NAS
Then, when she gets money,
she just thinks about spending it on you.
She doesn't think about
spending it on herself.
I remember in the summer
we went to the ocean.
I said, "Mom, I need a surfboard."
And she's like, "Are you kidding?
We don't have any money."
And I'm like, "Mom, I want a surfboard."
And she says, "Okay."
I don't know where she took the money,
from buying her own clothes
for work or something,
and she buys a surfboard.
I'll never forget it.
We didn't have the money,
but she took it from
some place. She found it.
They will always find the
money for their kids, right?
BU BU MO LA KHYIM 'BOGS PA
Then later, and this is very
common all over the world.
Someone told me yesterday, what was it?
It's a good friend of ours.
He's already planning for his son's house.
His son is two months old.
He's like, yeah, we're
going to buy a house,
we're going to buy him a house,
we're going to get a mortgage,
we're going to take care of the mortgage.
He's going to have a house
when he gets to 30 and
we give him the house.
I'm like, oh my god, the
kid was born two months ago
and the parents are already
planning the mortgage
just for the kid, just to
give the house to the kid.
So your mom, KHYIM 'BOGS PA
means they set you up with your own house
for your own family.
MNA' MAR BRDZANGS PA
means, for girl children in Tibet,
they arrange for your husband,
they got you married to
a good one, like my wife.
RAB TU BYUNG BA'I SGOR BCUG
Or they took you to the monastery
and made you into a monk or nun.
In Tibet, it was one out
of six people was ordained,
a million people were ordained
by the time of the cultural revolution.
RANG LA 'KHOS KA GANG YOD
PA'I BKA' DRIN GYIS BSKYANGS
They took whatever money they
had and they spent it on you.
So try to, I know in the modern world
there's a lot of people
who feel like their parents let them down.
They didn't treat them
nice, their parents were...
Why do you think your
parents were fighting?
They were stressed out. Why?
Because they're trying
to make money for you.
Yeah, they fought.
Yeah, they drank alcohol.
Yeah, they smoked cigarettes.
Because they were exhausted
taking care of you.
So don't be so righteous
about your parents.
If they were tired, and grumpy,
and fighting, and drinking,
it's because of you.
So if you don't have
anything to feel bad about
you can feel bad about that.
MDOR NA RANG GIS SHES TSAD DANG NUS TSAD
Your mom used every ounce of her brains
and every ounce of her physical energy
to find food and housing for you.
That was her thing. She
didn't do anything else.
Most of her time was spent
trying to find these things for you.
TSAD DANG NUS TSAD KYIS PHAN
BDE GANG YIN 'BAD PAS SGRUB
She just struggled to do that.
GNOD PA DANG SDUG BSNGAL SEL
BAR BYED PA SOGS KYI DRIN TSAD
And on the other hand,
she's trying constantly to
protect you from yourself.
Don't take those drugs.
Did you have this lecture from your mom?
Look, you can have a girlfriend,
okay, you can have sex,
but please learn about birth control.
She tried to protect you from yourself.
Like with the drugs, my
mom would say about drugs.
She said, "Look, now,
you can't hurt yourself,
I don't want you to hurt yourself."
DE BZHIN DU PHA SOGS SEMS
CAN GZHAN THAMS CAD KYIS
KYANG DRIN GYIS BSKYANGS
Then there are other people in your life.
Your father did a lot,
your uncles and aunts,
your grandparents, your school teachers.
Start to expand the awareness
of how many people took care of you
and tried to keep you out of trouble.
BSKYANGS PA 'DRA BA YIN, DE
LTAR SEMS CAN THAMS CAD KYIS
MI'I RTEN LA RANG GI MA BYAS
PA GCIG PU 'ANG GRANGS KYIS
MI CHOD
Even if you don't count all the times
that you were in a different
body, like a bird or a fish,
even just in your human bodies,
your human mom and your human dad
took care of you countless times.
And they did. They purposely
and voluntarily took on the
struggle to support you.
And of course it's an emotional struggle,
of course it's a physical struggle,
but it's a financial struggle also.
And they decided to do it.
They decided to have a baby, mostly.
DE'I TSE YANG DA LTA'I MA
BZHIN DRIN GYIS BSKYANGS
And you're even, DA LTA'I MA
in those past lives, your present
mother did the same thing.
My mom who struggled in this life
to make money for me in this life,
also struggled to make money
for me in my past lives.
DE BZHIN DU 'GRO BA GZHAN GYI
MA BYAS SKABS KYANG RI DVAGS
Then you can start going,
expanding the circle of your gratitude
to the times when this
same woman took care of you
in a different body, like a horse,
or like a deer, or something.
So now recognizing that in a human body,
she struggled for the money for you
in a human body countless times.
Let's start going to the other bodies
in which she did the same for you.
And Pabongka Rinpoche takes the example
of a wild animal, like a deer.
In that wild animal's
body, DE'I MAR BYAS TE
she served as your mom,
BYAMS PA'I LAS THA NA'ANG
and she showed you the same kind of love
that this human mothers did.
THA NA'ANG even down to,
LCES BLDAG PA
means to lick your body with her tongue.
And we have a picture of that I think.
I was looking for a picture
of a cow licking her calf,
but I ran into this camel picture
and it was kind of more powerful.
So this little camel was just born
and the mom is licking the
liquids off of the baby,
just after birth. She has this instinct.
So try to think of how
many millions of times
your mom licked the afterbirth off of you
as an animal.
BLDAG PA TSUN CHAD KYIS BYAMS PAR BSKYANGS
That was the beginning of her career
of affection for you for a whole lifetime,
as a camel, for example.
BYA LTA BU'I MA BYAS SKABS
Let's discuss times when
your mom took care of you
as a bird.
You were a baby bird
and she was a mama bird.
MA BYAS SKABS KYANG
ZLA BA GCIG TZAM GSHOG PAS RUM
She spent a month keeping you warm,
both as an egg and as a chick.
So in the nest, she laid there
with her wings purposely covering the egg,
even before you were born.
Then after you were born, RUM here
means like, what do you
call that inner fire?
GTUM MO, it means GTUM MO.
She kept you warm with her body warmth.
Both as an egg and after
you came out of the egg.
MIS DBYUG PA SOGS KYIS
And if, and I remember this,
so I had a kid who lived next door to us
when I was a small kid, and he was bad.
He was just a bad kid. He was a mean kid.
He would say, "Let's go kill birds."
I went with him once
and he would take a small gun,
BB gun, or something like that.
And he would go find nests
and he would shoot the bird.
If the bird had kids in
the nest, she will not fly.
She will cover the
babies and she will die.
She will purposely die.
She knows she's going to die,
but she will cover the babies
and she will wait for the gun.
And that's what he's talking about here.
DGRA BYAS PA NA'ANG
Even if somebody comes
up to threaten the bird
with a DBYUG PA
DDBYUG PA here means Danda.
This is the Tibetan for Danda,
DBYUG PA
If someone comes up with a
club and threatens to beat,
to kill the bird,
DGRA BYAS PA, RANG NYID
GSHOG PA YOD PAS 'PHUR NUS
the mother herself RANG NYID
has a GSHOG PA, she has wings.
She can 'PHUR, she can fly away.
MOD, but she stays and she covers the baby
with her body.
BU LA GCES NAS
Here's the GCES in RANG GCES 'DZIN, Tim,
in Seiji's text, which is?
Self-cherishing. BU LA GCES
to the child.
She has self-cherishing for the child.
SROG KYANG YAL BAR DOR
YAL BAR DOR
means she will abandon her own life,
if it means protecting her
child, even a bird will do that.
SRUNG
PHYIS NAS 'BU GCIG LAS MA RNYED
If you both survive long enough
and she can't find food
and she finds one worm.
And here's our picture.
'BU GCIG LAS MA RNYED means,
even if she finds a single worm,
if she can't find any
more than a single worm,
BYIN NAS GSO BAR BYED
she will give it to her child.
She will give it to the
baby and she will go hungry.
A mother bird will go hungry
and she will give the
single bug to her kid.
What's this GSO mean, you guys, you nuns,
she will GSO the child with the bug.
Rakshita
Sustain, and this is the GSO in GSO SBYONG
which means to fix your
vows or sustain your vows.
DE LTAR YANG THANG RE
THANG GNYIS TZAM MIN PAR
It's not that your mom
did that for you once.
protected you once or twice
at the cost of her life.
GNAS SKABS THAMS CAD DU
DRIN GYIS BSKYANGS PA LA
GRANGS KYIS MI CHOD
Every single lifetime
that she was your mom,
she protected you,
and you cannot count the
times that she died for you.
SNGAR MGO LOG GI JAG PA ZHIG
MGO LOG is a place
in East Tibet, famous for bandits.
And MGO LOG
which is a tribal name
almost means bandit.
JAG PA means a bandit,
someone who robs travelers.
That's their specialty.
JAG PA
RTA ZHIG LA GRI BTAB PA
They were having a fight,
he stabbed somebody's
horse with a big knife.
LTO BA LA THEBS TE
RTE 'U means a baby horse.
What do you call?
A foal.
LHUNG BA
This is the LHUNG BA
that you see in the monks and nuns vows,
which means downfall.
@THUNG BA or LHUNG BA
So what happened to the
colt or foal? LHUNG BA
It fell out of the womb.
The bandit cut open the
stomach of another guy's horse,
And then a baby, foal came out, called,
SHI KHA MA
means in the throes of death.
While she was dying,
the mother horse was licking the baby
as she was dying. She was worried
that the baby wouldn't
be clean or something.
So she's dying and she's licking the baby.
RTE 'U LA LCES BLDAG
There's the same LCES BLDAG we had before.
Lick with her tongue.
BYAMS PA
she had BYAMS PA for the foal.
She showed her love.
MTHONG NAS, when the JAG PA MTHONGed that,
he GCOD PAed, RDO RJE
GCOD PA his JAG PA LAS,
his career as a bandit.
He stopped his career as a bandit.
And he said, "God, this is me,
now I can't do this anymore."
So I guess in Tibet, it's a big deal.
I guess it's like a car salesman
starting to tell the truth or something.
But he's like, "I can't do this anymore."
He gave up his JAG LAS
his bandit career.
GCOD
He gave it up BYUNG BA RED
Pabongka Rinpoche loves
to tell little stories
that he's heard around Tibet.
And I think if you're teaching Lam Rim,
you should also tell your own stories.
That's part of the tradition.
Whatever stories happen in your life
that you can use to
illustrate the Lam Rim,
like the Mongolian wild kids story.
Then use it, it's okay, it's good.
It makes it more real for your audience.
They don't have robbers on
horseback to talk about, I hope.
DE'I DUS KYI RTE 'U DE RANG YIN LA
What if that baby horse was you?
What if the baby horse
that the MGO LOG bandit
chieftain saw getting linked was you?
RTA DE GZHAN 'DI MIN PA'I NGES PA CI YOD
MIN NGES PA CI YOD
means there's no certainty at all,
that you were not that baby horse.
You yourself was not the baby horse
that Pabongka Rinpoche is talking about.
There's no certainty that you
and I were not the baby horse.
And there's no certainty
that someone around you now
was not the mother dying
horse who licked you.
There's no certainty that
we are not the horses
that Pabongka Rinpoche is
describing in his story.
CI YOD, DE LTAR TSE 'DI'I
MAS RANG LA DRIN GYIS
JI LTAR BSKYANGS PA LTAR
So, we've established
that your mom struggled
to take care of you
financially, emotionally,
educationally, logistically in this life.
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD KYIS KYANG DRIN GYIS
DE BZHIN DU BSKYANGS PAR BSAM
You have to contemplate how
every other living being
has also done the same for you,
in many lifetimes, in countless lifetimes.
It's a sweet meditation to do.
It's a sweet practice to do.
You know we, sometimes we feel depressed.
I was depressed yesterday, I was sick.
Stuff happens in our life
and we feel kind of sad about life
or things aren't going so well.
And it's always a nice,
you have the option
if you're a Lam Rim participant,
if you've studied Lam Rim,
or if you've heard Lam Rim,
you always have the option to just sit
and think about the
horse and the baby horse,
and to think that everybody
around you has licked you
as their baby horse.
And I think you'll find that
this Lam Rim meditations
will make you very cheerful
and grateful to other people.
So then the Lam Rim
has an immediate effect
when you're feeling depressed,
or you feel low self-esteem,
just imagine getting licked
by everybody in the room,
when you were a baby horse.
And it's true, you were, and
try to cheer up a little bit.
I mean, we have all
taken care of each other.
We have all given up our lives
for each other countless times.
So, life is not so serious
and life is not so bad.
See you in the next Lam Rim.